In the previous lesson we learned that
classes are reusable, so
we're able to target more than one element
with a single class selector.
Now the other thing we need to know about
classes is that an element can
have multiple classes assigned to it.
So let's take a look at a practical use
case for using multiple classes.
At times, we may have a lot of repeated
CSS in our style sheets.
So sometimes, it's best to create classes
for the repeated styles.
For instance, here's a simple example.
So let's say that our primary content in
footer elements need to
have the same top border styles as the
secondary content element.
Now should we repeat this border top
property two more times in
our style sheet by adding it to the
primary content and footer rules?
The short answer is, no we shouldn't.
So what if instead, we created a new class
called t-border for top border.
Then, we'll add this border-top
declaration to the .t-border rule.
So, I'll just go ahead and remove the one
inside .secondary-content and
paste it inside the .t-border declaration
block.
So now, we can save our style sheet, and
in our HTML we can add that .t-border
class to those elements.
So right after the primary-content value,
we'll add a space then write t-border.
And now we can do the same for our
secondary-content class.
So we'll scroll down to the div on line
24, and right
after that secondary content class we'll
add a space, and add the t-border class.
So, for our footer, we'll need to add a
class attribute,
because currently it only has an ID.
So, right after the ID of main footer,
let's add a class attribute, and
then we'll make the value t-border.
Okay, so now when we save our index.html
file and
refresh the preview, there we have the
border styles in our primary content,
secondary content and main footer element.
And what's great is that we only had to
write the top
border declarations once in our style
sheet.
So doing this makes our CSS more
maintainable,
especially on larger sites because we're
not unnecessarily repeating lines of code.
So say we had to change the border color
from lightgrey to something like blue.
Well instead of changing the color in
three different selectors,
we only need to change it in one.
Now in a later course,
we'll get into the specifics of why we
should avoid repeating a lot of CSS.
For now, just know that it makes things
more maintainable for us.
So let's change our top border color back
to lightgrey.
And since this secondary content rule is
no longer in use, we can just go ahead and
delete it from our style sheet.
So one more important thing we need to
know about class selectors is,
we're able to apply both a class and an ID
to an element.
In fact, we did that earlier in the
footer.
As we can see we have the ID of
main-footer and the class of t-border.
And we did it up here in our header
element.
We have an ID of top and a class of
main-header.
But let's keep in mind that IDs carry more
weight than classes,
because they refer to something very
specific.
So if an element has an ID and a class
applied,
the styles defined in the ID selector will
always carry more
weight than the styles defined in the
class selector.
And if we're not careful about how we use
classes and
IDs, we can end up overriding styles in
class selectors.
That's why we need to make sure we do not
share the same
properties between classes and IDs.
And I'll show you a quick example of what
can happen.
So back in our style sheet, if we scroll
up,
I'll just write this above main-header.
If we target the ID of #top, then give the
element a background color of red.
So we will say background-color, and make
the value red.
When we save our style sheet and refresh
the preview.
We can see how the red background color
and
the ID overrides the one in the class
selector.
So again, we need to make sure that
elements are not sharing the same
properties in a class and an ID.
So I'm actually gonna remove the ID
selector of #top, since we
don't want it conflicting and overriding
the styles in the main-header class.
[BLANK_AUDIO]